good morning everyone in our today's session we will be focusing on proximal lesions of the posterior teeth and we shall learn how to perform aesthetic restorations in these clinical manifestations of curious lesions using dental composites
despite significant improvements in composite systems and adhesive systems since their introduction posterior restorations still require a careful placement technique in order to avoid micro leakage post-operative sensitivity or less than ideal anatomy marginal adaptation and micro leakage
prevention is most critical at the gingival margin which is determined by the accident of lesion itself the formation of an adequate contact during the insertion of class 2 raisin composite can be particularly challenging as the
lesion extends more gingivally in more superficial lesions such as this one it's comparatively easier to manage because of its relationship with the incidental tissues size of the lesion is directly related to the prognosis as
a matrix adaptation is easier which can securely engage and provide optimum seal at the gingival floor as the lesion size increased and as it extends more gingivally the more challenging the situation is
as the preparation is enlarged resistance form as well as bonding variables must be kept in mind during preparation metricing and restoration because whenever there is some kind of root involvement there will be some bonding
issues because of less mineral content maybe we are trying to bond on a cementum and the root dentine already has very less mineral content and higher collagen content so that's why there will be some
bonding issues uh next we'll there will be some isolation problems because whenever there is a class two lesion depending on the size there are some inflamed papilla incidentally
and these inflamed papilla uh produce exuded the inflammatory exit which can interfere with the etched or newly prepared surface another variable is the depth of light penetration in these regions if the depth is greater there will be
lesser chances of a proper light penetration and hence there will be less degree of conversion and because of less degree of conversion there could be some uh problems with the bonding or there could be some uncured composite there
are chances of secondary lesion as well as post treatment hygiene maintenance problems because there are chances of overhanging in this region as well to build up the proximal wall and the insertion of class 2 composite
restoration requires proper meta rising for a good contact formation hence correct use of enamel and dentine etching bonding steps and incremental placement of the raisin composites
and careful finishing is extremely important anatomically correct and tight contacts are difficult to achieve with resin restorations because resin composite materials are not condensable like amalgam the use of amalgam matrix bands like flatmate
for composite restorations generally leads to a straight point contact that are located in the occlusal third of uh the tooth which leads to under contouring of the situation as you can see in this illustration if i'm using a
flat matrix it is it is not going to create a contoured proximal contact so hence we are getting a flat contact which is not ideal uh remaining under contoured restoration will lead to overstimulation of the tissues
the matrix systems for composite materials are designed to create curved proximal surfaces and tight contact areas these are generally comprised of thin contoured matrix bands and a tooth separator you can see that it is creating optimum
contours in the proximal contact area so after restoration it is producing an anatomical contact which is an ideal contact talking about the indications these are almost the same indications whenever doing a composite restoration
in the posterior region again small and moderate restorations preferably within enamel margin is advised most premolars in molar restorations particularly when the aesthetics is in high demand a restoration that does not provide all
the occlusal contacts is generally weaker and a restoration that does not have a higher occlusal contact or the patient is not suffering from any para functional habits a restoration that can appropriately isolate during the procedure if you
cannot perform adequate isolation there is a very bad prognosis of these kind of restorations uh some restorations that may serve as foundations for crowns and some very large restorations that are used to strengthen the remaining or weakened
structure when the operating site cannot be appropriately isolated i told you that these are among the contraindication because if you will do the restoration there will be minimal um curing in the gingival region there are
chances of bond failure in that region so it's always contraindicated that you use some other materials such as you can try a sandwich technique by using resin modified in these areas prior to use
any composite uh whenever there are some high occlusal forces because of pair functional habits this is among the contra indications uh patients who are having high carry susceptibility and the patients who are with poor oral hygiene the composites
are contraindicated in these situations so again whenever we are talking about the advantages uh aesthetics is the number one advantage followed by um we are not removing a lot of tooth structure as we
are trying to do in amalgam which requires a strict geometry in order to get ideal retention and resistance form and with composites it is easier and less complex with preparation and since we are using
bonding system it is providing insulation and the composite itself is an insulating material there is a decreased chance of micro leakage because of use of bonding adhesive system
and we are also reinforcing remaining tooth structure by using composite and adhesive dentistry among the disadvantages if not used carefully uh there will be some polymerization shrinkage effects some post op sensitivity or debonding if
you have not followed all the recommendations during the preparation and etching and bonding process with some materials there is a low fracture toughness and it is quite a technique sensitive and time-consuming as compared to amalgam
and it is also expensive than amalgam so these are among the disadvantages so the problems with composites for use in class 2 restoration is number one it's difficult to it's not impossible
but it is difficult to achieve moisture control but if you are using rubber dam you don't have to worry about that and in deep sub-gingival extension areas uh adaptation of the matrix band and deep margin
elevation and these are all difficult procedures to attempt for so next we'll discuss the clinical techniques for class 2 composite restorations as you know the shade of the tooth is the most important parameter when aesthetics is a paramount
the shade of the tooth should be determined before the teeth are subjected to any prolonged drying because dehydrated teeth become lighter in shade as a result of decrease in translucency minor or no tooth preparation
it may be necessary to clean the operating site with a slurry of pumice to remove the plaque pellicle and superficial stains along with the calculus deposits if there are knowing the pre-op occlusal relationship is paramount for optimum
restoration so we shall mark the occlusal marks before any restorations local anesthesia should be provided to make more pleasant and uninterrupted procedure it also resulted in marked reduction in salivation isolation is extremely important for a
successful composite restoration although with cotton rolls and other means of indirect isolation composite restoration can be performed but it's highly unpredictable in this pictorial you guys can see this wedge application in the teeth
each matrix band should be secured with a wedge a wedge is needed to maintain adaptation of the matrix to the tooth and the gingival margin to avoid the overhangs and prevent adjacent tooth from getting nicked with high speed
handpiece excessive wedging forces are unnecessary when an additional two separators such as rings will be used so inserted wedge where the embroidery is wide from buckle to lingual or from lingual to buckle coming towards the benefits of the
wedging are the pre-wedging will cause slight separation incidentally it depresses the interdental papillae it controls hemorrhage prevent oozing of gravicular fluid it seals the matrix gingivally and it also ensures the tight contacts think before drill
so we'll coming towards the tooth preparation wedging of the proximal contacts to prevent the adjacent tooth and to prevent the overhangs and the restorations creating access to the faulty structure with your high speed handpiece
removal of the faulty structure convenience form for the restoration and then the retention is obtained by the bonding tooth preparation for class 2 has decreased pulpal depth of axial walls which allows greater conservation of tooth structure
a closer and proximal wall converge occlusally and provide additional retention form from the vertical movements proximal box preparation has a cable surface angle at right angle to the enamel surface facially or lingually bevels are given on the occlusal surface
and that are optimal due to the letter optional due to the direction of enamel rods whereas proximal surface beveling must be done prudently gingival floors should clear the contact apically and they should be butt joint
after the tooth cavity preparation the metric system is selected based on the operator preference the cavity location and the size if the contact is not opened during the tooth preparation
then conventional matrices materials may be simpler to use rather than the curved matrix bands and the separating rings if you are using a toefl my retainer
then always pre-burnish your band using a ball ended burnisher to create a slight contour at the contact point otherwise it will create a flat contact
which is under contoured again and not ideal in larger cavities a circumferential band can be chosen over sectional bands ultra thin curved or self-retaining circumferential bands enhance the ability to form tight curved contacts areas
and should be used rather than the traditional circumferential amalgam matrix bands and a toefl my retenders if the tooth is in irregular position and number ear shapes can sometimes prevent seating of the ring
it is useful for a dentist to have a variety of separating rings with different tine shapes with round or rectangular cross sections for a better fit in some buckle or lingual embryos
when a metric system and a separating ring is used the metric position should be verified prior to the application of the morning agent and resin composite material a properly matrix tooth should no gap
shows no gap along the gingival margin between the tooth and the matrix band the problems with the matrix use always pre-controlled metrics to form a proper contact point
if you use a straight matrix it will also make a flat surface and it will retain it like under contoured restoration your metric should be passively and shouldn't deformed
if the matrix is deformed again the restoration will be deformed because you're going to pack in the restoration when it's been maturized always remember your matrix retainer tines should be inserted below matrix and the wedge to hold
the tooth from the transitional line angles or the spots let's discuss some clinical aspects of class 2 restorations class 2 is a challenge why it is a challenge the reason being is what i feel in my whole clinical
practice that to find an actual tooth is a problem patient complains that food is trapped but most of the times when you examine that situation clinically the ridge remains intact
so to find a real culprit is a problem for the dentist for that you have to evaluate class to cavity in five different aspects but before examination you have to ask the patients to have some scaling in the
polishing as you know that poor oral hygiene is a leading cause of the class 2 cavity so with lot of calculus and the plaque you cannot examine you can miss some details during examinations so after
scaling and the polishing what five factors you have to evaluate see any redness and inflammation around that area that indicates there is some food trap areas there so it leads to inflammation of the gums
see any roughness of the tooth surface that is only possible if you dry the tooth and the surrounding tissues do floss to evaluate the contact points
then the next thing is evaluate if there is any discolorations like in that picture there is a visible discolorations on the measles aspect of the molar but the bridge is 100 is perfectly fine so you have to evaluate
all these things in the final you have to go with the bitewing radiograph that is the recommended radiograph for the class 2 inspection so as i told you that in previous slide there is a black discoloration on the
occlusal aspect so when you open the cavity there is a visible carious lesions so you need magnifications and you need proper evaluations with drying of the soft tissues and dental heart structures what is an ideal contact as we know that
in posterior teeth the contact is on the buccal sides and at the junction of the occlusal and the middle third but here the contact between two premolars is good and but the contact between
premolar and the molar is full of defects the ridge is intact but there's a lingual carious lesions for that because that area was just filled with some plug so when you ask the patient go
for scaling and the polishing then that area visible to you so you have to follow the protocols like that one that's a very clear picture there's open contact and the food trap is visible there when there is
food lodgement there is demineralizations and that demineralizations leads to demonization of the dentine and then enamel gets unspotted and then fractured with mastications which is recommended but for class 2 cavity preparations that's a round bar
round diamond and round carbide but remember that when you prepare the occlusal surface always use a small round bar with a high speed handpiece but when you go deep close to the pearl
when there is a chance of pulp exposure always use a small round but in slow speed handpiece with air water spray and if you feel that the tails are compromised you cannot evaluate a d part
of the cavity stop the water coolant use only air coolant so that the main purpose is just to cool the denting and avoid overheating of the denting what is the best way to isolate in a
class 2 cavity the picture that's visible here it's androgyny cavity it's occlusal cavity for that you can isolate a single tooth but for the class 2 you have to isol isolate multiple teeth so
then pass the rubber dam so here the cavity is still dirty and there's lot of a soft carries there we have to remove it we have we don't have to leave any carries there because that
carries is a weak part of the tooth that can lead to debonding of the composites so here you can see the cavity is very clean there is no demonization left there there is no dark carries enamel is
sound dentin is sound that's an ideal cavity to restore with the composites and always remember that the contact should be opened between premolar and the motor for the passive placement of the matrix because the wall of the shape
of the wall of the proximal side is always dependent on the shape of the matrix but when the matrix is deformed then the shape would be deformed so you have to place a passive matrix and the
shape of the matrix should be preserved so next we just pass the two metrics simultaneously and enter proximal wedge in between and we will build one wall at one time and as you see in the picture
the times of the matrix retainer should be in between the matrix and the wedge so we will fill one wall and then we will remove the matrix from that wall
and shift the matrix retainer to the next next tooth so here one wall is constructed no the matrix lines have been shifted to the molar and always remember that you cannot build a two wall
simultaneously the reason being is i told you already that the thickness of the matrix can lead to the gap in between the two molars so one wall at one time and remove the matrix and shift
the times the next one so here uh the class two has been converted into class one so now we have to restore the central part now
so the base of the cavity should be filled with the flowable around about one mm increments and then remaining part of the box should be filled with two millimeter increments the packable packable composites and we
just did the cruiser part uh cusp bikers so the occlusion of the patients them is a priority for a dentist it should be preserved a crucial part should not end into a flat restorations that can create
a problem in mastication so here is a post-op situation uh the very well adapted composites the contacts are the tight and there is no carious lesions visible so that's an ideal contact that helps the patient
domestications and then there would be no food trap in between the molars so that's so after doing uh clinical work uh the next thing is to evaluate your work with some radiograph that radiograph helps you to evaluate
your proximal contacts and cycle part of the restoration that remains open in most of clinical situations when you don't adapt the matrix well so that radiograph helps you to evaluate the performance of your
restorations so guys at the end of the lecture i want to recommend you few things and bitewing is a recommended radiograph for class 2. you cannot take a periapical radiograph to evaluate the carious lesions
as we know that periapical is only good for peripheral area it don't tell you details about the carious lesions and the extent of the restorations so bitewing is a recommended one
and the second thing is use a round diamond and round carbide for the cavity preparations i told you already that when you try to open the occlusal cavity in the crucial surface you use a round
diamond in a high speed hand piece but when you go near to the bulb always work in a very precise way need a round diamond but in slow speed hand piece and always drill the cavity in a brushing
actions don't drill drill drill okay and then important thing is that you always prepare a cavity with air and water spray but if you cannot visualize the details so you can just close the water
coolants and just work with the air coolant so next thing is don't prepare cavity without a wedge that's very important thing because interproximal wedge not only protects your soft tissues but also protects the
neighboring tooth during cavity preparations because most of time what happens when you don't use a wedge you can drill the adjacent well adapted tooth that once once there is a drilling so there is a process of demineralization
starts so you have to avoid this thing and the wear should be wooden it should be triangular it should be tight enough but if the wedge is not tight you can wrap wrap up the wedge with some teflon
tape then the most important thing is always use a pre-contoured matrix for class 2 restorations because shape of the matrix resembles the shape of the proximal wall don't use a toefl mat
because always ends in a flat restorations and finally guys nothing is a challenge until you work work work and you have to work for the rest of your life thank you guys